Enough!
Poor devil.
Luckily he had time to pay.
Better go, they'll blame me anyway.
The evening train?
Of course. Money moves in the shadows.
Enough. I called the police.
But we're colleagues!
Get going!
Terrorist!
Please come in.
I regret the trouble.
Fine cauliflowers.
I'd like this one.
Marcel?
You little gangster.
Oh Yvette, you were in.
Your bill's long
like the Congo River.
I'm your best customer.
When will you pay?
When I inherit. But don't tell my wife.
I'm the man of the house. Excuse me.
- Closed.
- I see your feet.
Impossible, I'm upstairs.
I'd buy something.
Good night!
Evening, Laika.
I'm home.
I notice that.
You've been busy today.
It's my nature.
I don't know how to be idle.
I'll prepare the dinner
but you've time for an aperitif.
Don't spend it all.
I'll take the dog.
She can carry the change home.
His name's Gérard Lenormand,
not Lebreton.
Amusing. You talk about a name,
but it's a culture.
- Brittany is a culture.
- No.
What culture?
You think Mont Saint-Michel
is in Brittany.
It is in Brittany.
It's Le Couesnon.
It's a fact.
You know, back home in Alsace.
Enough about Alsace.
Fine ducks there.
What you talking about?
That's heresy!
I'll go earn my pension.
Really tough to wake up at 4 am.
A pleasant fellow.
How's Arletty?
Fine. She's preparing dinner
and drove me out.
You don't deserve such a good wife.
You're not worth her.
No one is, so I'll do.
She's protective
and couldn't watch me lie in the gutter,
a man in his prime.
Foreigners see bums
in a considerably
more romantic light
than we French.
You're not too polite.
Her first husband was violent
and an athlete.
Care for another?
There's still time for one.
You're listening to Reality Radio:
Difficult Choices.
We talk about dishwashers.
Our guest is Annette Verdoux
from Electroflash.
Good evening.
This affects five million consumers.
How long does a dishwasher last?
Recent studies show that
their lives are being
deliberately shortened...
Won't you eat?
I visited Florence today.
She had a pot of cassoulet.
- What is it?
- More living dead.
The container was shipped
three weeks ago
from Libreville in Gabon
to London.
Was supposed to take five days.
Been here two days.
- A computer error.
- Probably in Paris.
Inspector Monet, Le Havre.
You heard voices inside?
More like a child crying.
Baltic Queen.
Wasn't she scrapped?
This is number two.
Former Honolulu Star.
What d'you think?
If they've had water and oxygen,
with luck...
Is that necessary?
Ministry of Interior's orders.
The Red Cross.
How are you, Madam?
And the child?
Tired.
Are you mad? A child.
ONE OF THE CONTAINER REFUGEES
ON THE RUN
ARMED AND DANGEROUS?
CONNECTIONS TO AL-GAEDA?
Salut, Marcel, ça va?
- Caught any?
- No. Dry as the Gobi.
Eskimos have robbed everything.
Greedy devils.
See you later.
Is this London?
You want there? The other side.
This is Le Havre, in Normandy.
Are you hungry?
Get up here.
Could be a pensioner's Metro card.
No Metro in Le Havre. Papers.
A black boy
has been seen here.
He needs care.
So you always say.
I've seen no one.
Beat it.
Don't forget your lunch.
Nothing here.
This morning, ruthlessly
and without warning
Le Jungle was destroyed.
Migrants regrouped behind banderols.
No Border activists and the police
clashed violently.
Two groups were formed:
underage youths, and adults.
No solution is proposed.
Just like with the earlier camp,
nothing but the press releases
were prepared.
Migrants, activists and
the journalists waited.
This morning
there were only 300 refugees
those with no other place to go.
A few weeks ago there were almost 1,000.
Refugees are no more in Calais,
but the problem is not solved.
Many of those arrested
will soon be released.
They look for new sites,
just like in Sangatte.
Almost ten years to the day.
Minister for Immigration came to Calais
to witness the camp's demolition.
The operation was not aimed
against the refugees.
A YOUNG BOY ON THE RUN
What do you think?
Hard to say, for I don't exist.
Who's he?
That's you, Chang.
I'm not Chang, not from China
but from Vietnam.
Came here 12 years ago atop a train.
Paid eight years for an identity
in the databases.
I can enjoy social security
and vote, if I want to.
I support my family,
I'm a happy man.
But I'm not him.
You can call me Chang, I'm used to it.
Mediterranean has more
birth certificates than fish.
It's harder to deport a nameless person.
The evening train comes soon.
- Evening, Marcel.
- Jeanne.
A sandwich and water.
Water?
It's not for me.
I understand.
What is it? Wait.
Marcel.
Turn off the stove.
What's wrong?
You weren't in the bar.
No one knew where you were.
I'll get an ambulance.
Don't be long.
Yvette!
What is it?
May I use the phone?
Arletty must go to the hospital.
I'll take you.
I'll just get my coat.
The husband of Arletty Marx?
Yes.
She sleeps, we gave her pain-killers.
You can go home.
Return when we get the results.
I'd like to wait.
That'd be no use.
You'd just be in the way.
Take my card.
Thank you.
Good morning, Yvette.
How's Arletty? What did they say?
She sleeps.
I go back in the afternoon.
Shall I come?
I'll be alright.
Perhaps they'll let her come home.
Perhaps.
Laika?
Came to pay your debt?
You have a name?
Speak.
Idrissa.
Quo vadis, Idrissa?
What?
- Where are you going?
- London.
What's there?
You know the way?
We'll talk later.
I must go, but I'll be back.
You can sleep on the couch.
Don't go out, don't open the door.
Understand?
Yes, Sir.
So there's no hope?
Miracles do happen.
Not in my neighbourhood.
Please don't tell the truth
to my husband.
Embellish it.
He's just a big child.
It's against the rules.
I beg you.
Tell him...
later.
The rules don't say when you must tell.
Alright.
I'll talk like a politician.
We'll begin the treatments next week.
Be brave.
I was too categorical.
There's always hope.
Doctor.
Come to see me later.
Yes, Dr Becker.
I didn't bring any food.
- How are you?
- Much better.
I almost got worried.
I'm away for a moment
and you start spending.
I got them cheap, they were on sale.
What am I saying?
I bought the most expensive ones.
Will you come home soon?
I'll take care of you.
I must stay, perhaps a long time.
The doctor will explain.
Let's talk about other things.
Thank God it's benign.
No danger then.
That's what the doctor said.
Evidently extremely benign.
Still, they won't let her home.
They want to be certain.
Care for another?
No, thanks.
On the house.
In that case, gladly.
I'll visit her tomorrow.
You remember the ward?
Thirteen, same as the room.
I'll go in the morning, too.
Santé!
Thank you.
Are you mad? You don't listen at all.
No wonder they put you on the ship.
Sorry.
If caught, you won't get to London
but back where you left from.
You want that?
No.
I need time to help you.
Central Police Station?
I believe I have
some information for you.
Are you hungry?
Did you eat anything?
Yes.
- Want some water?
- No.
I take a glass sometimes.
Does you good
and helps you to sleep.
I used to live a Bohemian life in Paris.
My success was artistic only.
We could drink a lot
if we had a cause to celebrate.
You don't understand?
No, Sir.
Don't call me Sir.
We haven't been introduced.
My, my. A civilized family.
Father was a teacher.
Marcel Marx. Call me Marcel.
Oui, mon Général.
I'll step out, then we'll continue.
Into the bedroom.
Evening, Yvette.
I brought some food.
I'm not hungry.
But someone inside might be.
A one-egg omelette nature
and a small red wine.
Right away, Mr. Marx.
Mind if I join you?
Nothing could please me more.
Domaine de Courbissac, 2005.
You live alone, Mr. Marx?
With my wife. Why?
She's in hospital?
Leave my wife alone and go.
What a temper.
Prefer to talk at the station?
On what grounds? My permit's fine.
As your tax declaration, I'm sure.
You misunderstand me.
I came as a friend, to warn you.
About what?
Your neighbour, for example.
I investigate crimes,
not taxes or immigration.
Understand?
Good day.
Marcel! Wait!
Thank you, Yvette.
Could you hide the boy if necessary?
Of course, gladly.
Don't tell anyone.
Of course not.
What do you...
Mr. Marx!
Come here.
I've sometimes been rude,
but times are hard.
I have groceries going old
and I thought of you.
Sit down.
I need names. Who are your parents?
Where do you come from?
Start from the beginning.
Do you know Mahamat Saleh's family?
Go over there.
I'll write down instructions for you.
Finish the polish with a cloth.
This one?
Yes. And do it well.
I need them tonight.
There are better professions
but besides shepherd's,
it's closest to people.
And the last to respect
the Sermon on the Mount.
Put a leash on Laika.
Will you take him? I'm off to Calais.
- How long?
- A few days.
Don't let the boy out.
Buy him some clothes
and make him take a shower.
Don't worry.
Thanks, Yvette.
I have important things to do.
I can't come tomorrow.
I'll tell you later.
Stay brave.
Your taxi will be here soon.
There's a camp on the shore
off Dunkirk.
I know.
- Do you know Mahamat Saleh?
- Talk to him.
May I disturb you?
Got a cigarette?
Sure.
- Want to eat?
- Thank you.
I'm looking for Mahamat Saleh.
I heard he'd be here.
Who told you?
His compatriots in Le Havre.
For what reason?
For his grandson.
Why should I believe you?
Because of my blue eyes.
He's not here.
He was taken to a refugee centre.
Which one?
The one here, in Calais.
His brother! Are you mocking me?
I'm the family albino.
And to your misfortune,
a journalist and a lawyer.
Discrimination based on the colour...
I never...
Don't make it worse.
I recorded everything.
- Fetch Mahamat Salem.
- Yes, Director.
The boy's mother has been
in London for a year already.
She has no residence permit
but a good job in a Chinese laundry.
The address is:
Whitechapel Road 248, at the back.
- Remember?
- I'll write it down.
My son was going to follow
her soon with Idrissa
but...
He was...
He died.
And what will you do?
The jar returns to the well
until it breaks.
I'm an old man anyway.
But if you can...
I give you my word.
I'm not alone. I've friends.
Please let me know.
Don't let them deport the boy.
I won't.
A wonderful child. Full of life and joy.
My cousin has a daughter
with a man
but they're not married.
Our family had a similar tragedy
in the fifties.
Isn't it wonderful that two
young people love each other?
Why should the society dictate
what's right or wrong?
Police?
The boy is at the railway station.
- Stay there.
- Let me go!
Wait peacefully.
The police are coming.
- Run!
- Listen, you!
You'll be in trouble.
Idrissa has disappeared.
- I checked your home, too.
- When?
This morning. I was in my shop.
Calm down. I'll find him.
Good afternoon, Laika.
Where's Idrissa?
- You been crying?
- No.
Good. It won't help.
Greetings from your grandfather.
He's well and told you to obey me.
He stressed that.
One moment.
Enter.
Marcel,
you mustn't see me like this.
Like what?
So thin and ugly.
You've said you hate thin women.
Ones who don't appreciate food.
Thin is even better.
How come?
For example, clothes take less fabric.
In a small car, you've room for more.
So you'd like more wives?
You want to misunderstand me.
Chocolate?
There you see.
You're truthful? It's not serious?
I wouldn't deceive you.
If you say so.
More than that.
I promise.
But now the treatments begin
and I must be alone.
I must not see anyone.
Not even me?
Especially not you.
You upset my equilibrium.
Would that be bad?
Extremely bad.
Come back in two weeks.
And when you come,
bring me my yellow dress.
The one I wore in La Rochelle.
Remember?
I remember.
But according to St. Matthew 12.
We're not unanimous.
St. Luke says
the kingdom of heaven is happy
and the gates open for the innocent.
But Christ returned onto Earth.
Good afternoon, Inspector.
Good afternoon, Mr. Prefect.
Please sit down.
The press follows this case closely.
It is imperative
that we progress quickly.
Yes, Mr. Prefect.
You have a long career.
Very long.
You are our best crime investigator.
Deliver the boy to the authorities.
The sooner, the better. For all of us.
I understand, Mr. Prefect.
Goodbye, Mr. Prefect.
Go inside.
A certain Marcel Marx lives nearby.
Tell me about him.
With pleasure. One of my best customers.
Regular as clockwork.
Won't let an unpaid bill keep him awake.
Wife in the hospital?
Yes. Poor woman.
I heard there's no hope.
How does Marx take it?
Crushed. Puts on a brave face.
Anyone else with him?
No one. Just a dog. Poor beast.
Misses her mistress.
Thank you.
I only did my duty. I love the society.
Won't you buy something
Inspector?
A pineapple.
A pineapple it is.
A calvados.
Leave.
Evening, Henri.
For me?
No.
I heard about your husband.
My condolences.
Why?
He was a fatalist.
I put him behind bars.
That's what cops do.
He would've died anyway.
What do you want?
Marcel Marx. You care about him?
Yes.
Very much.
In the distance
a train rolled into view.
All compartments were lit,
the windows cranked down.
We began to sing a ditty,
we all wanted to sing.
We sang faster than the train ran.
We waved our arms,
voices were not enough,
we ended up in a pleasant throng
with our voices.
When your voice mixes with others,
you're hooked.
We sang into the ears
of the distant passengers.
Grown-ups were still awake,
mothers prepared beds.
We had to hurry.
I kissed the one next to me,
offered my hand to the nearest three.
I began to run back along the road,
no one called after me.
When they could see me no more
I turned and ran along the farm roads,
into the forest again.
I went south towards the town
of which we said:
"Strange people live there!
They don't sleep!"
"Why not?"
"They don't grow tired."
"Because they are mad."
"Don't mad people grow tired?"
"How could the mad grow tired?"
She's asleep.
My cousin's brother-in-law will do it.
We could swap cargoes
in international waters.
But it's expensive,
the risk is big.
The boat may be confiscated.
For us, it's enough if you pay the fuel.
And the Englishman?
3,000 Euros.
I'll get the money
but I need a bit of time.
Thanks, Francis. I won't forget this.
An enormous sum.
I've saved up some.
Yvette doesn't deserve to inherit.
She's so reckless.
To open up a bakery
during times like these.
I've saved up 200
for my daughter's bike. It can wait.
She's only two weeks old.
Thank you, but I really couldn't.
I'll have to manage.
Arrange a charity concert.
It's very trendy.
But I can't play at all.
- Hire Little Bob.
- Impossible.
Why?
He won't play until Mimie returns.
Has Mimie left?
Yes. They had a row.
About what?
Gardening. An apple tree, apparently.
How long has she been gone?
Three weeks now.
Where can I find this Mimie?
Alright, if Roberto apologizes.
Thank you, Jacquotte.
I know you've had differences
with your wife.
But I'd like to arrange
a trendy charity concert
with your help.
Only if Mimie comes back.
Without her, my voice lacks substance.
She's the road manager of my soul.
What did you argue about?
It was insignificant.
But she must understand
who's the man of the house.
It can't be her.
What if I can persuade her to come back?
I could dance a minuet.
Mimie.
Oh, Roberto.
The Return of Little Bob
- Hi, Idrissa.
- Mr. Chang.
We're waiting.
What do you mean?
The concert begins in four hours.
What concert?
Are you drunk?
The Little Bob concert you arranged.
But it's tomorrow.
According to the poster,
band and audience, today.
Shit.
Idrissa.
Take this to my wife in hospital.
Her name's Arletty.
Tell her I'll come tomorrow.
Listen carefully,
I'll explain how you get there.
- Can I help you?
- Room 13?
End of the hall.
Come in. Looking for me?
Are you Mrs. Arletty?
It's from Mr. Marx.
He can't come today,
he'll come tomorrow.
And who are you, if I may ask?
Idrissa Saleh,
a friend of your husband.
What brought you here?
I came by accident.
Have you known Marcel for long?
No. Just a couple of weeks.
Madam.
Yes?
Try to get well soon.
Mr. Marx won't manage without you.
I think so, too.
Madam.
Goodbye.
And good luck.
Goodbye. To you, too.
Thank you.
You'd better go.
Inspector Monet, what a surprise.
And this early.
It's my nature.
May I come in?
By all means.
The dark side of my work is
that people don't like us.
People scream for us to help.
But are they grateful?
Not a bit.
It doesn't really bother me.
I don't much like people.
But it seems to disturb my colleagues
especially the younger ones.
It may be hard to believe
that my heart has its tender spots.
I'm ruthless towards genuine malefactors
but I don't like to see the innocent suffer.
Not you. You're not innocent.
And have never been.
That is true.
Naturally,
I'm here completely unofficially
and I thank you for inviting me in.
A nasty wind blows outside.
And I couldn't give you advice
without committing a breach of duty.
Naturally.
So, we agree.
On my day off, and as your friend
permit me to think aloud.
Here, it's your privilege.
If I were you,
you find that repulsive...
On the contrary.
Don't exaggerate.
If I practised smuggling,
this is just hypothetical,
and I had a precious parcel
the border police should not get,
they deal with smuggling
and illegal immigration.
Your hypothesis is interesting.
So if I were you
I'd get rid of the parcel
as soon as possible.
Goodbye.
Gauthier, Goupil, Hébert, the street.
The rest, follow me.
Stay there.
Madam, we'll check the premises.
Go ahead, gentlemen.
We'll check the premises.
Talk to my wife.
With pleasure, young man.
Good morning.
Good morning, Jean-Pierre.
True. It goes well with scallops.
Yes, but you have to shell them
and make the sauce and everything.
Right, I won't make scallops.
They follow you.
I know.
Is the boy safe?
Hope so. God willing, he leaves today.
A white.
May I go out the back?
Lock the door, Luc.
Go.
- Cauliflowers!
- Sold out.
Go and sell your stuff to the rich!
I'm sorry.
What a greengrocer!
Liar!
My husband'll kill me.
Have a nice voyage.
Get going, Chang!
Thank you. I won't forget you.
Nor will I you.
Greet your wife for me.
Take this.
Your mother's address.
Thanks, Francis.
- You dirty...
- Don't make it worse.
Do you smoke?
Move aside.
The hold is empty.
I've my orders.
You question my authority, officer?
No, Inspector.
You may go.
I was mistaken about you.
May I apologize with a drink?
Why not.
Perhaps a calvados.
Follow me, Mr. Marx.
You can pick up her things later.
Corinne, take him to Dr. Becker.
Right.
I'm sorry, Mr. Marx,
I don't know what happened.
Medicine knows nothing like this.
Everything pointed at the opposite.
I heard about a patient in Shanghai
who had healed in seconds...
but here in France...
I'm cured.
The disease is gone.
Let's go home, Marcel.
Look, Marcel.
The cherry tree blooms.
I'll make dinner right away.
Subtitles: Mikko Lyytikäinen